1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration Collection
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
- 6. Publications, 1884-2009; 2.5 linear feet 3 Box (Box 6 -, Box 8)
  - Subseries 6.1: Ephemera, 1884-1909; 0.5 linear feet 1 Box (Box 6)
    - Newcomb Hudson-Fulton Celebration Booklet #3, Thin outer cover is very brittle. Crease in bottom right corner of cover. Creases in upper and bottom left corners of back and along left edge. Small creases in cover along spine. (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Saddle stitch bound booklet with a thin, striped translucent outer cover. Front cover of booklet features image of “Half-Moon” on Hudson River. Back cover features advertisement for DuxBak Belting produced by Chas A. Schieren Company, New York. Inner pages feature images associated with Hudson and Fulton along with the celebration program of events. Copyright Newcomb Publishing Co, New York, 1909.
    - Newcomb Hudson-Fulton Celebration Booklet #4, Missing thin, outer cover. Fraying of edges and corners. Small creases along spine. Staples are slightly rusted. (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Saddle stitch bound booklet with front cover featuring image of “Half-Moon” on Hudson River. Back cover features advertisement for DuxBak Belting produced by Chas A. Schieren Company, New York. Inner pages feature images associated with Hudson and Fulton along with the celebration program of events. Copyright Newcomb Publishing Co, New York, 1909.
    - Hudson-Fulton Celebration Banquet Booklet, Ribbon used for binding is frayed in several places. Faint staining across front and back of cover. Tear in upper right corner and small spot along bottom edge. Spine has begun to fray. (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Informational booklet from Hudson-Fulton Celebration Banquet on September 29, 1909. Booklet features information on celebration, such as other countries involved and visiting fleets. Cover of booklet features the seal of The Hudson-Fulton Celebration Commission. Booklet is bound with tri-colored ribbon featuring the colors of the Dutch flag.
    - Hudson-Fulton Celebration Banquet Booklet #2, Discoloration along bottom edge of outer cover. Creasing throughout. Two more prominent creases in upper corners and across center from top bottom and left to right. Staining along crease on back. Small stain on bottom right edge of back. Paper is fragile. Some rust on staples. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Hudson-Fulton Celebration Committee Brief History Booklet, Severe water damage to the inner pages. Possible mildew across front and back cover and along edges of leaves. Front cover missing upper right corner. Several other small tears along top and right edge of front cover. Several tears along edges of back cover. Bottom staple very rusted and has discolored paper around it. Spine has cracked and there are small tears around staples and at the top and bottom. Staining in upper left corner of back cover. Handwritten note across top of front cover. (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Booklet produced by the Hudson-Fulton Celebration Committee to provide a brief history of Hudson and Fulton’s journeys in coordination with the Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Inner pages also feature names of members on the committee the proposed schedule for the celebration and other suggested activities during the celebration. Brief history written by Edward Hagaman Hall L.H.M.
    - Hudson-Fulton Celebration Committee Brief History Booklet #2, Small tear in center right edge of front cover. Various small stains along right edge of front cover. Discoloration around edges. Small spots of foxing on back cover. Fraying of edges and corners. Staples are rusted. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Official Souvenir of HF Historical Pageant, Fraying and tearing of edges and corners. Small spots of foxing on both front and back cover. Small stain on upper left edge of front cover. Small crease on second hole on spine. Large tear in top left edge. (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Twine bound booklet produced by Redfield Brothers Inc. to commemorate the Hudson-Fulton Celebration Historical Parade. Inner pages feature information about the various floats and parts of parade. Front cover features imprinted lettering and image of Hudson’s “Half Moon”. Booklet compliments of National Enameling & Stamping Company, New York.
    - Official Souvenir of HF Historical Pageant #2, Fraying and tearing of edges and corners. Small crease in upper right corner of front cover. Large crease and tear in bottom left corner of front cover, Small tear in bottom right corner of front cover. Tears and creases along spine—more significant tears at top and bottom. Faint staining on front page. Large stains in upper left of back cover. Tear along bottom center edge of back. Ends of twine have frayed. Several creases across image. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Official Souvenir of HF Historical Pageant #3, Fraying and tearing of edges and corners. Small crease in upper right corner of front cover. Large crease and tear in bottom left corner of front cover, Small tear in bottom right corner of front cover. Tears and creases along spine—more significant tears at top and bottom. Faint staining on front page. Large stains in upper left of back cover. Tear along bottom center edge of back. Ends of twine have frayed. Several creases across image. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Official Souvenir of HF Historical Pageant #4, Fraying and creases in corners. Small creases along bottom edge of front and back cover. Ends of twine have frayed. Small tear in upper left corner of front. Discoloration around edges of front and back cover. Several creases across image. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Official Souvenir of HF Historical Pageant #5, Creasing of both upper and bottom right corner. Creasing in bottom right has creased all leaves of booklet. Small tear in spine at top and bottom. Fraying along top edge and corners. Two small stains along right edge—one at top and one at bottom. Faint foxing across image and across title page. Staining across back cover. Ends of twine have frayed. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - NYS Education Department Hudson-Fulton Celebration Booklet, Fraying of edges and corners. Small stain on bottom right edge of front corner and on bottom right edge. Large crease and various smaller creases in bottom left corner. Small creases along spine. Staining across bottom edge of back cover. (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Saddle stitch bound booklet produced by the State of New York Education Department in 1909. Front cover depicts image of view of Hudson River from West Point. Inner pages feature information and images about Hudson, Fulton, the celebration and general information the Hudson Valley and NYS government. Back cover features official seal of Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
    - NYS Education Department Hudson-Fulton Celebration Booklet #2, Fraying of edges and corners. Tears along right and left edges of cover. Small tear on front right edge of cover extends to first few pages. Possible faint foxing across front cover. Large crease on the left of front cover. Cover has started to left away front text block around staples. Several creases and cracks along spine. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - NYS Education Department Hudson-Fulton Celebration Booklet #3, Cover is separated from text block. Back end leaves still attached to back cover. Bottom left corner of front cover missing. Fraying of edges and corners. Tears along all edges of cover. Several creases along edges of cover. Large tear in bottom left corner of title page. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - NYS Education Department Hudson-Fulton Celebration Booklet #4, Back cover and end leaves missing. Fraying of edges and corners of remaining cover. Small tears and several creases in bottom right corner of cover. Small creases and tears along spine. Several creases in bottom right corner of title page. Faint staining across front cover. Group of small stains in upper right of cover. Faint, small stains along inside cover and title page. Title page image has stained inside cover. Staining on title page from cover image. Image on page two has stained page three. Faint staining across back. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - First National Bank HF Souvenir Program, Front cover of outer box is missing most of top, right, and left edge and entire bottom edge. Tear in bottom left edge. Staining across front and back cover of box. Large stain across center of front. Tears along remaining edges of box. Foxing across front and back of box. Large stain on left center edge of back. Smaller stains on upper left and right corners and along top and right edge of back. Faint staining across front cover of booklet. Staining on back of front cover of booklet from art on second leaf. Faint blue stain on bottom right edge and in bottom right corner of back of second leaf. Faint scratches on back of leaf too. (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Saddle stitch bound booklet featuring program for Hudson-Fulton Celebration and several advertisements for products and businesses in the Albany, NY area. Front cover features images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont” above banner for Hudson-Fulton Celebration and dates for the celebration in Albany, NY—October 7-9, 1909.
    - HF Staten Island Banquet Menu, Fraying of ends of twine and corners of cover. Golden seals have begun to fade and patina. Faint staining across back cover. (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Twine bound booklet featuring speakers, menu, and the festival song. Front cover features images of Billopp House, “Half-Moon,” “Clermont,” Hudson, and Fulton. Cover also features feminine figure in center above title for banquet and the date for the celebration—Thursday, September 30, 1909. In the center of each edge of cover features a different golden seal. Inner menu is in both English and French.
    - Godey’s Lady’s Book February 1884, Paper is brittle. Staples from binding have rusted and area around them has deteriorated. Front several pages has damage to top and bottom right corners. Bottom right corner of front page is detached, but remains with magazine. Significant and various tears along edges and corners. Fraying of edges and corners. Small stain on front cover in upper right corner. Faint staining along edges of front cover. Front and back cover are missing. Back pages have significant tears in bottom right. Small spots of foxing throughout. Large crease in bottom center to right edge of front cover. Large creases in back top left corner. (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Godey’s Lady’s Book Volume 108, Number 644, Philadelphia, February 188. Features piece by Augusta de Bubna title “Sub Rosa: A Valentine”. Saddle stitch binding.
    - Hudson-Fulton Pageant of Dramatizations Booklet, Discoloration around front cover edges. Various small stains along right, center edge of front cover. Various creases along spine. Various faint scratches across front and back covers. Faint across back. Two small, darker stains on back bottom left. These two stains have bled through to back page of text block. Larger stain along top of back and small stain along top edge and upper left corner edge. Creases in corners. Fraying of corners. Small tear along upper right edge of front cover. (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Saddle-stitch bound booklet featuring script and music for Hudson-Fulton Pageant of Dramatizations. Booklet was published by Hinds, Noble, & Eldredge Publishers 31, 33, 35 West Fifteenth Street, NYC. Booklet features blue cover depicting image of Hudson’s “Half-Moon” on the Hudson River.
    - Albany, NY Hudson-Fulton Souvenir Booklet, Fraying of edges and corners. Spine has cracked and is fragile. (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Large booklet featuring information about the Hudson-Fulton Celebration in Albany, NY on October 7-8, 1909. Cover features portraits of Hudson, Fulton, and a Native American man with background of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont”. Back cover features image of a modern man and Native American man above the word “assiduity” in the center of artwork depicting elements of the Oneidas, Onondagas, Senecas, Cayugas, Tuscaroras, and Mohawks. Cover art designed by F.M. Hill. Book is bound with the saddle-stitch method.
    - Albany, NY Hudson-Fulton Souvenir Booklet #2, Small, but significant tear in bottom edge. Small tear in right edge. Front, bottom corner missing. Back, top left corner missing and damage done to back few pages. Top corner of pages has significant creasing. Staining along edges. Small brown staining along front, bottom right edge. Spine has begun to rip and staples have begun to rust. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Ter-Centenary of the Hudson Booklet, Twine is fraying on the end and the dye used has begun to fade in spots. Small stain on front cover along right bottom edge and along bottom left edge. Small stain on back cover on left center. Tape remains along back top center edge. Small tear in top center edge, as well. Faint staining across inside cover page. Fraying of edges and corners of cover. Crease in bottom left corner of front cover. (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Booklet bound with red twine featuring yellow flowers on cover. Published in commemoration of Hudson-Fulton Celebration and is titled “Ter-Centenary of the Hudson and Centennial of the Steamboat”. Inside includes information on Hudson and Fulton, but also various landmarks throughout the Hudson Valley and advertisements for local businesses.
    - Hudson-Fulton Celebration Program Board of Alderman Souvenir Booklet, Fraying of edges and corners. Faint staining along edges of front cover. Various small creases across front and back cover. Various creases and cracks along spine. Staples on spine have rusted. Spine is missing top layer of paper and features small tears. Small crease in upper left corner of front cover. Very faint staining across back cover. Faint staining along edges of front cover. Faint foxing across inside of front and back cover. (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Saddle stitch bound booklet featuring decorative cover of American and Dutch flag overlaid with image of Hudson’s “Half-Moon” and the dates of Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Bottom banner on cover reads “Souvenir/ Board of Aldermen/ The City of New York”. Inside pages outline the program of events and those involved in each parade and floats used for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
    - Hudson-Fulton Celebration Souvenir Booklet, Large crease from top to bottom of right center of front cover—crease has also damaged first leaf of booklet. Inside cover has cracked along crease. Faint staining across front and back cover. Small stain on upper right of second leaf and center right edge of third leaf. Several creases and cracks along spine. Fraying of edges and corners. Discoloration along edges of cover more prominent along front and back top edge. (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Large booklet featuring cover with Dutch flag overlaid with lettering for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Center features images of Hudson’s “Half-Moon” and Fulton’s “Clermont”. Bottom left and upper right corner stamped with date “Oct 8- 1909”. Inner pages feature images and blurbs about celebration and landmarks along Hudson River. Front two pages outline information about Hudson-Fulton Celebration and the program of events. Saddle stitch binding.
    - Hudson-Fulton Celebration Souvenir Booklet #2, Faint staining across front and back covers. Fraying along edges and corners. Various small creases and cracks along spine. Two small stains on left center edge of front cover. Small spots in upper left and right corner of front cover where top layer of paper is missing revealing the white beneath. Three large creases in front cover from top to bottom-two in center one along spine. Large crease in center of back cover from top to bottom. Large stain on center bottom of back. Very faint foxing visible on back cover. Small stain along right edge of second leaf. (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Large booklet featuring cover with Dutch flag overlaid with lettering for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Center features images of Hudson’s “Half-Moon” and Fulton’s “Clermont”. Inner pages feature images and blurbs about celebration and landmarks along Hudson River. Front two pages outline information about Hudson-Fulton Celebration and the program of events. Saddle stitch binding.
    - Hudson-Fulton Ulster County Day Kingston, Faint staining across front and back cover. Fraying of edges and corners. Various creases and cracks along spine. Discoloration along edges of cover. Faint foxing across back cover. Small stain on left center of back cover. Various small stains on right bottom of back cover. Bottom staple on spine has slightly rusted. (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Large booklet featuring cover with Dutch flag overlaid with lettering for Hudson-Fulton Celebration in Kingston, NY on October 5, 1909. Center features images of Hudson’s “Half-Moon” and Fulton’s “Clermont”. Inside front pages feature information on celebration in Kingston and the program for the entire Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Inner pages feature images and blurbs about landmarks in Kingston, NY. Saddle stitch binding.
    - Newburgh, NY HF Celebration Souvenir Booklet, Fraying and small tears along edges and in corners of cover. Small tears near staples on spine. Faint staining across front and back cover. Top right corner missing on front cover. Faint staining on first and last page of text block. Large tear along top of spine. (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Bound booklet featuring program of events for Hudson-Fulton Celebration in Newburgh, NY. Inner pages also feature information on the local community and departments, such as Fire Department and City Council. Front cover features portraits of Hudson, Fulton, and images of both “Half-Moon” and “Clermont.” Back features maker’s mark from Newburgh’s The Daily News.
    - Tiffany& Co. Hudson-Fulton Celebration Banquet Booklet (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Booklet bound with three ribbons, each a different color to represent the Dutch flag (blue, white, and orange), for the Hudson-Fulton Banquet on September 29, 1909. Front cover features image of “Half-Moon” on Hudson River above small image of “Clermont”. Inner pages feature information on speakers for the evening, the menu, and those on the commission. Menu is in French. Booklet is with its original box.
    - Hudson-Fulton Celebration Official Program Booklet, Fraying and small tears along edges of cover. Potential water damage in bottom right corner of front cover and first few pages of text block. Bottom and top right corner of front cover missing. Tear in bottom right of page 15. Small stain on center left of front cover. Tears along top and bottom edge of back cover. Faint staining across front and back cover. Small stain on right edge of back cover, along spine. (Box 6Folder@7)
      Saddle stitch bound booklet featuring program for Hudson-Fulton Celebration and images and blurbs on official insignia and events. Front cover features image of “Half-Moon” and back cover features image of “Clermont”. Front title labels booklet as the “Official Program” for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
    - Hudson-Fulton Celebration Official Program Booklet #2, Large pieces of cover missing along front top right edge and back left corner—back piece is detached but present. Creasing in top and bottom right corner of front cover. Small tears along spine. Staples are rusted. Fraying of edges. Large creases in back cover from top to bottom. Large crease in back upper left corner. Large, faint stain along back top edge. Inner pages are creased throughout booklet. Outer cover is nearly detached from text block. (Box 6Folder@7)
    - Consumers Brewing Co. HF Celebration Souvenir Fold-Out Program, Small tears along right edge. Fragile along folds. Small hole on center left and bottom. Small, faint stain on center bottom. (Box 6Folder@7)
      Fold-out postcard featuring images of Hudson, Fulton below banner for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Fold-outs feature images of “Half-Moon” on Hudson beside Native Americans, the “Clermont” on the Hudson with colonial onlookers, and New York State landmarks, such as West Point and the Statue of Liberty. Back of card features program for events for Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
    - Consumers Brewing Co. HF Celebration Souvenir Fold-Out Program #2, Crease along bottom center edge. Small tear in right center edge and top right edge. Crease in bottom right corner. Small tear in top center edge. Small hole in each corner of center rectangle. Staining along center fold lines of back. Small stain on right center of back. (Box 6Folder@7)
    - King of the Air Sheet Music, Handwritten not on page for seating chart. Faint staining across front and back cover. Fraying of edges and ends of ribbon. Small tears in upper left corner of cover. Large stain on upper right of back cover. Slight fraying of edges and spine. Seal on front has stained through to back of front cover. (Box 6Folder@7)
      Booklet of sheet music for march and two-step arrangement of “King of the Air” by Julius K. Johnson. Front cover features man flying “The Hudson Flyer” aircraft. Back features advertisement for other pieces of music available for purchase.
    - Scientific American Vol. 101—No. 13, Fraying and small tears along edges and in corners. Booklet bound with possible tape. Tear in upper left corner repaired with tape on the inside page. Fragile along center crease. Faint staining across front and back cover. Discoloration and faint, red stain in upper left corner of back. (Box 6Folder@7)
      Issue of Scientific American released on September 25, 1909. Volume 101, Number 13. Inside pages feature information on the Hudson-Fulton Celebration, but also on both Hudson and Fulton. The inside articles also focus on the “Half-Moon” and “Clermont” and scientific specifications for each ship. Bound with saddle stitch method. Front cover features image of “Clermont”.
  - Subseries 6.2: Books, 1909-2009; 2.0 linear feet 2 Box (Box 7 -, Box 8)
    Books about or relating to The 1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration and items related to the celebration.
    - Fourth Annual Report of Hudson-Fulton Celebration Commission Vol. 1, Cover has several small stains throughout. Cover image has worn away along top and right side. Cover is almost entirely separated from spine and text block. Hinge is very fragile. Foxing across head and fore-edge. First few leaves and last few leaves all contain significant foxing. Inner leaves contain discoloration around edges. Staining along edges of front cover. Large stain on right of back cover. Smaller stains on left of back cover. Fraying of edges and corners of cover. Small scratches across head, tail, and fore-edge. Faint foxing across front cover. (Box 7)
      Clothbound book-style compilation of the Fourth Annual Report of the Hudson-Fulton Celebration Commission to the Legislature of New York. Report transmitted to the Legislature of May 20, 1910. Volume 1 contains pages 1-715. Printed for the State of New York by J. B. Lyon Company, State Printers, at Albany, 1910. Volume prepared by Edward Hagaman Hall, L.H.M., L.H.D..
    - Fourth Annual Report of Hudson-Fulton Celebration Commission Vol. 1 #2, Slight fraying of edges and corners. Faint staining across bottom of front cover. Large creases in top of spine causing creases in various leaves of text block. Small scratches across head, tail, and fore-edge. Severe staining of head. Faint discoloration along edges of inner leaves, tail, and fore-edge. Faint staining on back end leaves. Small stains on upper right and center left of back cover. (Box 7)
      Clothbound book-style compilation of the Fourth Annual Report of the Hudson-Fulton Celebration Commission to the Legislature of New York. Report transmitted to the Legislature of May 20, 1910. Volume 1 contains pages 1-715. Printed for the State of New York by J. B. Lyon Company, State Printers, at Albany, 1910. Volume prepared by Edward Hagaman Hall, L.H.M., L.H.D.